Guide to the F. O. Matthiessen Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- January 1967 Acquisition, 1900-1955, undated; 2; 4.68; (7 boxes)
  - Printed material
    - Pamphlets, magazines, circulars, and The Ancestry and The Descendant of John Pratt (Hartford Press: Hartford, 1900), circa 1900-1947; 28 (Box 12)
      Includes one folder of printed material on Matthiessen.
- September and October 1983 Acquisitions, 1901-1955; 3; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Gift of George Abbott White, 1983.
  Organized into two series: Correspondence and Writings.
  General note
  Formerly classified as Uncat ZA MS 353.
  - Correspondence
    - de Fletcher, Martha, 1949 (Box 13)
    - Dreiser, Helen, 1949 (Box 13)
      Includes drafts of typescript drafts of poems
    - Dreiser, Theodore, 1901 (Box 13)
    - Geismar, Maxwell, 1949 (Box 13)
    - National Guardian, 1948 (Box 13)
    - Naumbura, Edward, Jr., 1947 (Box 13)
  - Writings (Box 13)
    - Typescript drafts of reviews, speeches, dictionary entries, introductions to writings by others, circa 1920-1950; 30 (Box 13)
    - Introduction to The American Novels and Stories of Henry James, handwritten and typescript drafts with notes, 1947; 4 (Box 14)
    - Henry James: The Major Phase, typescript with notes, 1944; 3 (Box 14)
    - Notebooks of Henry James, typescript with notes, 1955 (Box 14)
    - Theodore Dreiser, handwritten draft with notes, 1951; 5 (Box 14)
- June 1984 Acquisition, 1930-1031; 4; 0.21; (1 box)
  Gift of George Abbott White, 1984.
  Formerly classified as Uncat ZA MS 354.
  - Translation: An Elizabethan Art, handwritten drafts with corrections and notes, 1931; 6 (Box 15)
  - Letter from Elinore Pollack-Ottendorff to Matthiessen, 1930 July 31 (Box 15)
- April 1985 Acquisition, 1941-1949, undated; 5; 0.21; (1 box)
  Gift of George Abbott White, 1985.
  Formerly classified as Uncat ZA MS 331.
  - "Horse-Racing Chief," typescript draft, corrected, undated (Box 16)
  - "On Book Reviews," typescript draft, 1948-1949 (Box 16)
  - Untitled essay, handwritten with corrections, undated (Box 16)
- February 1991 Acquisition, 1941; 6
  Gift of George Abbott White, 1991.
  Formerly classified as Uncat ZA File 257.
  - American Renaissance, draft consisting of holograph and typescript pages, mockups and proofs, corrected and annotated., 1941 (Box 16)
- June 1995 Acquisition, 1924-1945, undated; 7; 6; (6 boxes)
  Gift of Richard W. Hyde, 1995.
  Formerly classified as Uncat ZA MS 444.
  The folders were labeled and arranged according to Louis Hyde's arrangement.
  This acquisition consists of correspondence, writings and a small amount of other papers, collected by Louis Hyde in the process of writing Rat and the Devil: Journal Letters of F. O. Matthiessen and Russell Cheney (1988). The bulk of the correspondence is original correspondence between Matthiessen and Cheney, with some photocopies. Hyde's notes and handwritten labels are on the folders.
  - Letters from Russell Cheney to F. O. Matthiessen, letters 1-804, 1924 September 1-1929 February 28; 38 (Box 17)
  - Letters from Cheney to Matthiessen, letters 805-1549, 1929 March 1-1941 December 23; 45 (Box 18)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Microfilm service copies are available for select folders (film number 1188)
  - Letters from Cheney to Matthiessen, letters 1550-1746, 1942 February 17-1945 May 21; 10 (Box 19)
  - Letters from Matthiessen to Cheney, letters 1-527, 1924 September 16-1927 May 22; 21 (Box 19)
  - Letters from Matthiessen to Cheney, letters 528-1372, 1927 September 24-1945 May 13; 43 (Box 19)
  - Typescripts and photocopies of correspondence between Cheney and Matthiessen, 1924-1925; 16 (Box 20)
  - Letters to Cheney by various individuals other than Matthiessen, 1929-1945; 3 (Box 21)
  - Photocopies of Cheney/Matthiessen correspondence, undated (Box 21)
  - Various letters labeled "restricted", 1939-1947 (Box 21)
    Conditions Governing Access
    This folder is not restricted.
  - Rat and the Devil: Journal Letters of F. O. Matthiessen and Russell Cheney by Lewis Hyde, typed notes and related material, undated; 2 (Box 21)
  - "The Walsh-Sweezy Case," notes and pamphlet, 1938 (Box 21)
  - Printed material by or collected by F. O. Matthiessen, 1938-1948; 2 (Box 21)
  - Financial papers, including income tax returns and royalty statements, circa 1936-1940 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous writings by F. O. Matthiessen, including essays, articles and reviews, 1939-1945, undated; 4 (Box 21)
  - Russell Cheney by F. O. Matthiessen, galley proofs, undated (Box 21)
  - Teaching material, 1941-1943 (Box 21)
  - The Achievement of T. S. Eliot by F. O. Matthiessen, typescript and related material, 1935; 5 (Box 22)
  - American Renaissance by F. O. Matthiessen, typescript and related material, 1941; 7 (Box 22)
  - Henry James: The Major Phase by F. O. Matthiessen, typescript and related material, 1944; 3 (Box 22)
  - Unidentified writings and notes by F. O. Matthiessen, 1946; 2 (Box 22)